Guide to the Confederate War Etchings 1863-1864 PR 10-1
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Confederate War Etchings
1863-1864
PR 10-1
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.3 Linear feet 1 portfolio (29 prints): etching; sheet 27 x 21 cm. on mount 34 x 26 cm.
Caricatures, sympathetic to the Confederate States of America, drawn during the Civil War. These materials have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
1 portfolio (29 prints): etching; sheet 27 x 21 cm. on mount 34 x 26 cm.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Dr. Adalbert John Volck (1828-1912) was German-born and immigrated to the United States in 1848. He settled permanently in Baltimore in 1851, and worked as a chemistry instructor while studying to be a dentist. He practiced dentistry for many years in Baltimore. During the Civil War, he was sympathetic to the South, as were many other Baltimoreans. In an effort to combat the success of the Northern caricaturist, Thomas Nast (ironically also German-born), Volck issued many caricatures, sketches, and cartoons favorable to the South. The Confederate War Etchings are the most important and best known of these.
Scope and Content Note
This portfolio of twenty-nine caricatures was etched by Volck and was originally published under the name "V. Blada." The etchings have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Made during the Civil War, the etchings show sympathy for the Confederate cause, and distaste for warfare in general. It sardonically illustrates events that allegedly took place in the North and South from Philadelphia and Baltimore to Charleston and Vicksburg between 1861 and 1863. Lincoln's ideals and actions are caricatured, as are such topics as Union army conscription methods, Northern treatment of African Americans, and the behavior of the Union and Confederate armies. Northerners of conflicted views are shown in several scenes smuggling medicine to the South, or joining the Confederate army. Several scenes of events in Baltimore highlight the city residents' early ambivalence toward the war cause and effort.
The original publication contained thirty prints, but one plate, "Meeting of the Southern Emissaries and Lincoln," has been lost. The portfolio was produced in an edition of 200 copies for subscribers of Dr. Adalbert John Volck during the early part of the Civil War. An edition of 45 plates, including the original 30 and 15 additional by the same artist, was also pub. (with imprint, London, 1863) under title: Sketches from the Civil War in North American, 1861, '62, '63. By V. Blada [pseud.]
Arrangement
The caricatures were numbered by the artist, and are housed in a portfolio by this numbering system.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Many collections in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections document the Civil War. These include the Album File, PR 2; Graphic Arts File, PR 22; Poster File, PR 55; Stereograph File, PR 65; and Photographs of the War of the Rebellion, PR 88.
Caricatures; Confederate States of America; Etchings; Political Satire, American; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865-- Caricatures and cartoons
- Confederate War Etchings
  - Worship of the North, 1863; 1 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Passage through Baltimore, 1863; 2 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Writing the Emancipation Proclamation, 1863; 3 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Battle in Baltimore, April 19th, 1861, 1863; 4 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Searching for arms, 1863; 5 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Enlistment of Sickles' Brigade, N.Y., 1863; 6 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Buying a substitute in the North during the war, 1863; 7 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Marylanders crossing the Potomac to join the Southern army, 1863; 8 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Election in Baltimore, November, 1862, 1863; 9 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Stone blockade off Charleston, S.C., 1863; 10 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Making clothes for the boys in the army, 1863; 11 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Slaves concealing their master from a search party, 1863; 12 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Return of a raiding party from Pennsylvania, 1863; 13 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Valiant men "Dat fite mit Siegel", 1863; 14 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Tracks of the armies, 1863; 15 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Formation of guerrilla bands, 1863; 16 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Jamison's Jayhawkers, 1863; 17 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Smuggling medicines into the South, 1863; 18 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Offering of bells to be cast into cannon, 1863; 19 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Albert S. Johnston crossing the desert to join the Southern army, 1863; 20 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Gen'l Stuart's raid to the White House, 1863; 21 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Gen'l Stuart's return from Pennsylvania, 1863; 22 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Butler's victims of Fort St. Philip, 1863; 23 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Prayer in Stonewall Jackson's camp, 1863; 24 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Counterfeit Confederate notes publicly offered for sale in the "City of Brotherly Love", 1863; 25 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Free Negroes in the North, 1863; 26 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Free Negroes in Hayti, 1863; 27 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Cave life in Vicksburg during the siege, 1863; 28 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)
  - Vicksburg Canal, 1863; 29 (Map-case 17, Drawer 4)